From a place you never heard of...a story you'll never forget.
Gallipoli is a war, history, drama film directed by Peter Weir.
Two Australian sprinters face the brutal realities of war when they are sent to fight
in the Gallipoli campaign in the Ottoman Empire during World War I.
Frank Dunne, played by Mel Gibson.
Archy Hamilton, played by Mark Lee.
Jack, played by Bill Kerr.
Les McCann, played by Harold Hopkins.
Zac, played by Charles Lathalu Yunipingu.
Stockman, played by Heath Harris.
Gallipoli is a 1981 Australian war drama film directed by Peter Weir and produced by
Patricia Lovell and Robert Stigwood, starring Mel Gibson and Mark Lee.
The film revolves around several young men from Western Australia
who enlist in the Australian Army during World War I.
They are sent to the Gallipoli peninsula in the Ottoman Empire (modern-day
Turkey), where they take part in the Gallipoli campaign.
During the course of the film, the young men slowly lose
their innocence about the purpose of war.
The climax of the film occurs on the Anzac battlefield at Gallipoli, depicting
the futile attack at the Battle of the Nek on 7 August 1915.
Gallipoli, which had a budget of $2.6 million, provides a faithful portrayal of life in Australia in the 1910s—reminiscent of Weir's 1975 film Picnic at Hanging Rock set in 1900—and captures the ideals and
character of the Australians who joined up to fight, as well as the conditions they endured on the battlefield, although its portrayal of British forces has been criticised as inaccurate.
It followed the Australian New Wave war film Breaker Morant (1980) and preceded
the 5-part TV series Anzacs (1985), and The Lighthorsemen (1987).
Themes of these films include the Australian identity, such as mateship and larrikinism, the loss of innocence in war,
and the continued coming of age of the Australian nation and its soldiers (later called the Anzac spirit).
Gallipoli received heavy international promotion and distribution and helped to elevate the worldwide
reputation of the Australian film industry and of later Australian New Wave films.
The film also helped to launch the international career of actor Mel Gibson.
Due to the Gallipoli battlefields becoming tourist destinations in the 21st century, the film is
often shown at the hostels and hotels in Eceabat and Çanakkale on the Dardanelles.
In the 20 to 1 episode "Great Aussie Films", Gallipoli was listed as Number 1.
The film explores themes of australia, army, world war
i, battle assignment, british empire.
The tone is dark and emotional.